Register of the Ivan D. Yeaton papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ivan D. Yeaton papers
1908-1979
76013
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 7 envelopes (4.5 linear feet)
Memoirs, reports, memoranda, correspondence, orders and citations, charts, and photographs relating to Ivan D. Yeaton's military career; Soviet military strength in 1941; Soviet-American relations, 1941-1949; organization of American military intelligence during World War II; lend-lease operations; American relations with the Chinese communists, 1944-1946; and the inspection of United States Army procurement contracts, 1952-1953.
Yeaton, Ivan D.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976, with an increment received in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1919-1920 Lieutenant, American Expeditionary Force Siberia
1939-1941 Military attaché, Moscow
1942 Promoted to Colonel, U.S. Army
1942-1945 Specialist, Military Intelligence Division, War Department General Staff
1945 Chief of Intelligence, Headquarters, China Theater
1945-1946 Commanding officer, Yenan Observer Group, Shensi Province
1946 Assistant military attaché, Shanghai
1947 Assistant Director of Counter Intelligence, General Headquarters, Far East Command, Tokyo
1948-1949 Chief, Psychological Warfare Section, Plans and Operations Division, General Staff
1949-1950 Assistant Chief of Staff for Plans and Intelligence, Sixth Army, Headquarters, Presidio of San Francisco
1952-1953 Chief, Detroit Field Office, Army Inspector General
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, reports, memoranda, correspondence, orders and citations, charts, and photographs relating to Ivan D. Yeaton's military career; Soviet military strength in 1941; Soviet-American relations, 1941-1949; organization of American military intelligence during World War II; lend-lease operations; American relations with the Chinese communists, 1944-1946; and the inspection of United States Army procurement contracts, 1952-1953.
United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army--Procurement.; United States. Observer Mission to Yenan, 1944-1945.; Communism--China.; Lend-lease operations (1941-1945); World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; Soviet Union--Armed Forces.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Military attachés.
- MEMOIRS OF COLONEL IVAN D. YEATON (1919-1953), 1977 August (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Final bound, typewritten photocopy (with appendices). Written by Col. Ivan D. Yeaton, USA (Ret.), with editorial assistance from General A. C. Wedemeyer, USA (Ret.), Colonel Frank E. Mason, USA (Ret.), Major General Ralph C. Smith, USA (Ret.), and Charles G. Palm, deputy archivist at the Hoover Institution.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1961 (Box 1)
  Reports, memoranda, correspondence, orders, citations, charts, and other matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Biographical file of Ivan D. Yeaton
    - General
    - Kuomintang passport to enter Chinese Communist Party area (Yenan)
    - Personnel file, Office of the Assistant Military Attaché, Shanghai, China, 1946-1947
  - McFarland, Kermit
  - Richard Sorge spy case
  - Russia
    - Correspondence file of Ivan D. Yeaton as military attaché, Moscow, 1939-1941
    - Memorandum on the Soviet labor unions prepared for Ivan D. Yeaton, typewritten draft, undated
    - Report by Ivan D. Yeaton
      - "Russia Combat Estimate," typewritten, mimeographed copy, 1942 April 1
      - [Soviet petroleum production], typewritten draft, 1947 November 19
      - "Fourth International," typewritten carbon copy, 1947 November 26
      - "Northeast Asia," typewritten copy, undated
  - U.S. Department of Defense, Directive: Standards of Conduct, printed copy, 1961 December 12
  - Wedemeyer, A. C., General, "The Truth About Korea," national radio and television talk delivered in Los Angeles, California, typewritten, mimeographed copy, 1952 November 2
- MEMOIRS (1919-1953), 1974-1976 (Boxes 2-4)
  Additional material.
  - First typewritten draft, 1974 June (Box 2)
  - First typewritten draft with corrections by Ivan D. Yeaton, 1974 August
  - First typewritten draft with corrections by Ivan D. Yeaton, A. C. Wedemeyer, Frank E. Mason, Ralph C. Smith, and Charles G. Palm, 1974 September
  - Second typewritten draft (with appendices), 1976 January
  - Faymonville file (Box 3)
  - Ribbon copy of "Memoirs"
  - Bound typewritten photocopies of "Memoirs," 2 copies (Box 4)
  - Suggested changes for copies to be produced after 1977 August 8
- 1980 INCREMENT, 1908-1979 (Boxes 5-9)
  Writings, correspondence, orders, memoranda, notes, photographs, certificates, and memorabilia relating to U.S. military intelligence activities, the Soviet Union on the eve of World War II, the Chinese communists during the war, and post-war world politics.
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1947, 1953 (Box 7)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 February release of records, 1947, 1953
    Consists of materials used as appendices for "Memoirs": Memorandum, "The Control of Russia in the Event of an Unconditional Surrender," December 1947; typescript re "system of control to be established over the Soviet Union," 4 December 1947; and memorandum (photocopy), "General Motors Corporation: Acquisition of Industrial Facilities at Government Expense," 23 November 1953.